Guide to the WESU Records, 1943 - [ongoing]
WESU Records, 1943 - [ongoing]
Special Collections and Archives, Wesleyan University
WESU (Radio station: Middletown, Conn.)
2004-84
8.5
12
WESU was founded in 1939 as a student radio station. From 1967 until 1990, it operated under the purview of the Wesleyan Broadcast Association, independent from Wesleyan University, broadcasting on the FM band at 88.1 megahertz. In 2003, Wesleyan University acquired the license to broadcast at 88.1 megahertz, and WESU became a subsidiary thereof.
The WESU Collection contains documents, correspondence, and notes related to the operations of the station from 1943 onwards.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Given by Elizabeth Wolfe (Class of 2006) in 2004; Evan Simko-Bednarski (Class of 2007) in October 2005; and Rory Bradley (Class of 2007) in October 2005. Additional materials given by Aliza Simons (Class of 2009), May 2009 (accession number 2009-26) and July 2009 (accession number 2009-30).
Historical Note
What would come to be called WESU began in 1939 when two students living in Clark Hall connected a transmitter to a phonograph and began broadcasting short transmissions down their hall. As time progressed, the pair extended their broadcast range by illicitly attaching their transmitter to the network of water pipes beneath Wesleyan, slowly expanding until most of the campus had become an antenna. From these mischievous beginnings, the station quickly became a legitimate campus fixture, broadcasting throughout the Middletown area in the early 1940's on an AM signal under the call letters "WES". In 1950, updated Federal Communications Commission law granted the station its four-letter moniker "WESU." In 1967, WESU underwent two crucial changes-the station switched over to FM broadcasting, and its broadcasting license was transferred to the Wesleyan Broadcast Association, a non-profit corporation founded by the WESU Board of Directors as an entity independent from Wesleyan University. The years that followed saw an increase in non-Wesleyan involvement in the station, as members of the surrounding community came to serve as DJs and, by the mid 1990's, hold positions on the Board of Directors. In 1980, WESU precipitated a nation-wide college boycott of Arista Records regarding what the WESU board saw to be the unfair treatment of college radio stations. In 1990, however, the Wesleyan Broadcast Association forfeited its incorporated status. In 2003, Wesleyan University entered into negotiations to acquire the license back from WESU, and it succeeded. The years that followed saw the University's addition of NPR programming to the WESU broadcast day, and the University's reconfiguration of the WESU Board, removing non-Wesleyan community members from voting positions.
Collection Overview
The WESU Collection contains documents, correspondence, and notes related to the operations of the station from 1943 to 2000.
Series 1, WESU board minutes, contains the minutes of the WESU Board of Directors from April 1959-January 2000. There is also a significant amount of material from and pertaining to the 1967 incorporation of the Wesleyan Broadcast Association.
Series 2, Correspondence, Memos, and Clippings, primarily contains undated correspondence and memoranda.
Series 3, Subject Files, consists of policies, printed material, programming information, and descriptions of WESU's history.
Series 4, Financial, consists largely of receipts, invoices, bills and other miscellaneous material pertaining to the stations operating costs, as well as budget requests, bank statements and checks.
Series 5, Rock Biographical and Playlists, contains promotional material from bands and record labels, as well as several on-air playlists.
Series 6, Addition of May 2009.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
College radio stations --United States.; Radio stations --United States --History.; WESU (Radio station: Middletown, Conn.)
Related Material
Other sources of information on WESU include the Vertical (Subject) Files, Special Collections & Archives; The Argus, Special Collections & Archives; Olla Podrida, Special Collections & Archives; and The Gas Pipe Networks: a history of college radio, 1936-1946 by Louis M. Bloch (located in Olin Library, TK6548.U6 B56).
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1. Board Minutes
  - WESU Board Minutes, April 1959-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
  - WESU Board Minutes, Fall 1979-Spring 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1-20)
    There are no minutes from Fall 1993 to Spring 1994 or from Fall 1999 to Spring 2001.
- Series 2. Correspondence, Memos and Clippings
  - Listener Correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - External Correspondence, undated (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with University, undated (Folder 3)
  - Program Guide Requests/ Mailing List, undated (Folder 4)
  - Election Memos, undated (Folder 5)
  - Internal Memos, 1968 and undated (Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, undated (Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous/Memos, undated (Folder 8)
- Series 3. Subject Files
  - Policy, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Arista boycott, 1980 (Folder 2)
  - Training, undated (Folder 3)
  - Technical documents, 1978 and undated (Folder 4)
  - Staff lists, 1992-2000 (Folder 5)
  - Listener data, undated (Folder 6)
  - Show proposals, undated (Folder 7)
  - The Living Edge, undated (Folder 8)
  - Ephemera, undated (Folder 9)
  - Program guides and schedules, 1979-2000 (Folder 10)
  - Printed material, 1973-2000 (Folder 11)
  - Information/press regarding FCC Obscenity Law, 1986-1987 (Folder 12)
  - FCC Information, 1982-1998 (Folder 13)
  - Intercollegiate Broadcasting System Documents, 1979-1999 (Folder 14)
  - Blank forms (Folder 15)
  - Completed forms, 1980 (Folder 16)
  - I Will Make This Radio Work: Collected History and Advice by Mike Best '93 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Argus, newspaper, Olla Podrida clippings, Historical, 1943-1998 (Folder 2)
  - Historical, undated (Folder 3-4)
  - Computer printout, undated (Box 9)
- Series 4. Financial
  - Miscellaneous financial, 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Technical receipts, circa 1974-1985 (Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous financial, undated (Folder 4)
  - CBC Allocations, 1974-1975 (Folder 5)
  - CBC Allocations, 1975-1976 (Folder 6)
  - CBC Allocations, 1976-1977 (Folder 7)
  - CBC Allocations, 1977-1978 (Folder 8)
  - CBC Allocations, 1978-1979 (Folder 9)
    Missing Spring 1979.
  - SBC Allocations, 1979-1980 (Folder 10)
  - Disbursements (financial ledger), 1980 and undated (Box 9)
  - Disbursements (financial ledger), 1 May 1967 and undated (Box 10)
- Series 5. Rock Biographical and Playlists
  - Rock Biographical A-B (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Rock Biographical C-D (Folder 2)
  - Rock Biographical E-F (Folder 3)
  - Rock Biographical G-I (Folder 4)
  - Rock Biographical J-M (Folder 5)
  - Rock Biographical N-P (Folder 6)
  - Rock Biographical R-T (Folder 7)
  - Rock Biographical U-Z (Folder 8)
  - Rock Biographical Miscellaneous (Folder 9)
  - Playlists, 1979-1980 (Folder 10)
  - Playlists, 1981-1982 (Folder 11)
  - Playlists, 1983-1984 (Folder 12)
  - Playlists, 1985 (Folder 13)
- Series 6. Addition of May 2009
  - Program guides, circa 1990s, and personnel directory, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Flyer and letter, 1993
  - Program guides, 1990s
  - Program guides, 1980s
  - Program guides, 1970s
  - WESU Middletown: the Station Today
  - WESU minutes, circa 1998-2004
  - WESU Magazines, volumes 3-6
  - Production director email, 5 May 2009
  - Zines related to radio shows
  - 2009-2010 Board of Directors ballot and results (Box 11)
  - WESU Magazines, Volumes 1, 3, 5
  - WESU-FM: FCC Third Class Radio-Telephone Operators License (with broadcast endorsement) Study Guide
  - WESU: Random and interesting file
  - Program guides, 2000s
- Series 7. Addition of July 2009
  - Program guide, summer 2009 (Box 12)
  - Event posters (Box 12)
  - WESU Training Manual (Box 12)
  - Clippings (Box 12)
  - Bumper stickers (Box 12)
  - WESU Middletown: The Station Today, 15 May 2008 (Box 12)
  - Transmitter upgrade fact sheet, October 2008 (Box 12)
  - Democracy Now event sign up sheet, 10 December 2004 (Box 12)